software engineering radio episode 25
software architecture part 2
okay welcome to another episode of
software engineering radio this is part
two of the software architecture series
on the microphone is Marcus and Michael
and I think this is another one of the
relatively theoretical episodes where we
talk about concepts in later
architectural episodes we'll probably
talk more about practical issues the
first thing we want to talk about in
this episode is something we call
quality attributes or quality
characteristics or quality requirements
or non-functional requirements with
regards to software architecture so when
you build a software architecture then
you probably always have to make a lot
of compromises and if you have to
balance several requirements and those
requirements can be grouped into several
different categories there is for one
the runtime requirements runtime
characteristics of a system things like
performance scalability availability
usability and security then there is the
structural attributes things like
maintainability probability reusability
integrate ability and testability and
then we have the business aspects things
like time to market cost lifetime and
rollout schedule so we'll basically
first talk about the ill ''tis
performance ility probably is the term
that's still missing here so Michael do
you want to start explaining performance
yeah I the sort of with performance and
just to mention that like runtime of
attributes
there's also another term sometimes
regularly used called operational
requirements this term got used by Kevin
honey for example in article he called
insight requirements and structural
attributes like maintainability and poor
availability he calls and developmental
requirements okay but come back coming
back to performance performance well has
two kinds of flavors one is latency so
basically the timer system needs to
react on an external event and the other
is throughput on how many events for
example per second gets processed
through the system and latency is one
thing that is especially important in
real-time systems in soft real-time
systems it's not a big fault when a
deadline is missed so when the latency
gets exceeded but in in true hard
real-time requirements it's actually a
fault then when the latency gots to gets
too large and the deadline gets missed
on the other hand the throughput way of
measuring performance is more relevant
for transaction systems and business
systems as opposed to latency in
embedded systems okay and whether you
achieve high or low performance it's
dependent on a lot of things it's
dependent on your hardware on how well
you design your algorithms what kind of
algorithms you used want kind of
communication overhead head you have
inside and the memory available
bandwidth so all impacts in in some way
or the other
the performance of the system and it is
important to to mention that performance
is defined as we explained before at a
specific configuration of your system so
if you know that for example you have to
process a certain number of events in a
real-time system you can tune your
system so that it optimally performs for
this set of events so the performance is
specific for us for a certain
well-defined configuration of the system
yeah the the performance requirement
actually has to be associated with some
well-defined use case and configuration
so that you actually can measure than in
your system test or in your final
integration test whether you actually
achieve that performance so just a
single performance number without giving
a use case wouldn't be a good
requirement
for a development team another reason
why it's important to stress this
configurations thing is if we compare
performance with scalability which is
the next point we want to talk about
scalability describes the fact that a
system can keep its performance or
degrade only slightly if you put more
load on to the system now of course if
you have a certain configuration and the
system performs well then you cannot
expect to add 10 times the load and the
system has the same performance if you
keep the hardware the same so of course
scalability includes the idea that you
can add twice as many machines and your
performance is the same as before if you
load doubles or set the other way around
if you keep the system configuration
your hardware your resource is the same
then if you add twice as much load the
system should only get twice as slow or
half as fast the degradation of
performance over the load should be
linear or nearly linear and that is
especially important for enterprise
systems where the environment the load
on the system is not always known if you
start a website and you expect that you
have I don't know 1,000 hits per minute
or hour doesn't matter and then your
your website becomes more popular and
you get 5,000 hits per whatever time
period then of course you should be able
to to add a reasonable amount of
hardware so that things don't get too
bad or too expensive respectively the
next quality attribute we want to
discuss is availability and availability
is basically
a factor a percentage calculated by
taking the mean time to failure divided
by the mean time to failure plus the
mean time to repair so availability
means that your system should be up and
running at least that percentage of of
the time reliability on the other hand
is defined solely by the mean time to
failure so how often a failure occurs in
your system and that's really important
to mention if you have a system that
fails every hour but automatically
reboots using some kind of watchdog and
the reboot only takes a second and
people don't notice this outage time of
1 second then you probably don't have a
problem
there are many or at least several
embedded systems which do crash from
time to time but they're rebooting time
is so quick that the availability is
still very high right yeah
so you also have to define what actually
a failure is so it's a is a failure
already when you miss a deadline like in
a real time system or is low throughput
also considered to be a failure when the
system is basically not responsive to
user requests anymore right so one
should maybe extend the definition we
said before that the availability is
more or less the time during which the
system is up and running free of
failures maybe we should add and with
the specified quality of service right
yeah right because if a degradation of
quality of service constitutes a failure
then it's really really important to
give this term it's it's yeah you to
mention that term prominently the next
attribute we want to discuss is
usability and usability as some also
multiple kinds of flavors for example
learnability how long does it take for
an end user to learn on how to work with
the system or efficiency on how
efficient can a user actually operate
how is the user interface designed how
oh well can get the user get its job
done the other thing is a developmental
time how easy is the API to learn how
how does the API protect the programmers
from making mistakes this is basically
about a programming model and that the
API supports is this awkward or is it
just straight and and easy to get and
easy to get right actually yeah it's
it's really interesting to see these two
terms learn ability and efficiency
because it's often the case that a
system that is easy to learn so it's
quite obvious how to use it initially
it's not always very efficient if people
have to work with it a lot so this is
some of the reasons why web view eyes
and and rich clients are often
considered kind of more or less rather
different concepts because web UI eyes
are easy to learn but they're not very
efficient to use if you have to do a lot
of work with them so those two
specifically are often kind of in
conflict the last kind of flavor is the
memorability if that term mixes and that
is basically how well can a user
remember on how to achieve its task does
he have to search the buttons and menu
items every time when he uses the
application and didn't use it for a
while or is it just so easy that he
doesn't need to look up into how open
and browse around to find the right icon
right and again this probably ties into
learnability because if it's easy to
learn then it's probably also easy to
really learn which is more or less the
same as memorizing what you did before
the next requirement is a very diverse
one which is security and we probably
have to do a couple of episodes on
software security separately and also
you should listen to the security now
podcasts by the way but the point is
that there are different kinds of
security so first there is the
authentication problem so people or
users that haven't properly
authenticated to the system shouldn't be
able to use it the other thing is author
Rajon so once your user has been
authenticated so it's basically allowed
to use your system you have to specify
or determine which parts of the system
he can use and how which resources to
access which data to access which
functions which features to use this is
called authorization there are other
kinds of securities one is obviously the
thing that if you move your data over a
network you should probably encrypt it
you should be safe against various kinds
of hacking attacks things like trying to
exploit buffer overflows or another
problem is denial of service attacks if
you have a system that faces the web or
network your system should be robust
against denial of service attacks
although this is not trivial do you have
anything else to add to the security
thing no I thank you you covered it from
an high level and details will come
later in later episodes right so maybe
one last comment on security there is a
common understanding in the architecture
world and also in the security world
that it's probably not possible to add
security after the fact security should
be designed in from the start and that's
something that many people don't really
take to heart and so many systems are
not very secure because people thought
now we can add security after the fact
and then it didn't work out the next
developmental requirement is
maintainability that we want to discuss
and that is basically how well can you
extend or change your system after you
have deployed at once and for this it's
basically about refactoring that is a
term which got used lately in the last
few years intensively and it's about
removing features it's about changing
features changing and limitations
extending it to new scenarios new
requirements or just adapting the whole
solution to a new environment like a new
application server platform or a new
operating system a specific kind of main
nobility is portability you probably
want to be able to run the system on
various kinds of environments
specifically on different operating
systems and different Hardware on
different networks this is especially
important in the embedded world where
you usually have various configurations
of systems running on different hardware
platforms at least in the automotive
world we've had this problem regularly
and you have to do a lot of non-trivial
things to be able to run your system on
different environments the point is of
course that you should if you talk about
portability then you want to be able to
run the system
ideally simultaneously on those
different platforms simultaneously means
that you shouldn't have to manually
change your codebase in order to run it
on different environments so so
maintainability portability
both of these are about managing
variabilities and handling variabilities
and representing variabilities in your
system and the reason why I mentioned
that is that we will have a separate
episode later in this podcast about
variabilities and then even further in
the future about product lines which is
basically about formalizing those
variabilities even further another term
we want to define here is reusability
and this basically specifies how easily
parts of the system can be reused in
another system and that is also of
course the general reuse topic and
especially important in the context of
software product line software product
families where you have multiple
products based on the same components
based on the same core assets and you
want to reuse those parts maybe in
slightly adapted or configured versions
so reusability is not just about
inheritance but basically oo tried and
in my opinion never truly achieved the
reuse but it goes even further
of using basically all means to ensure
that a software software component can
be reused at a later time
another one is integrate ability it's
also rather strange term I guess so it
specifies by specifies how easy it is to
develop parts of the system separately
and integrate them later on
modularize ability could be another term
so at the point is if you have a big
system then it's unlikely that you can
develop all parts of the system in one
go in one team at one location and you
have to make sure that the separate
parts that you have to define can be
well separated then also and then later
on integrated together again well
testability is the next term and the
next requirement we want to discuss and
this is basically about how to make sure
that you can demonstrate that your
system does what it is supposed to do
that you can test it easily and that
starts off with unit tests module tests
until you reach the integration and and
system tests depending on how large and
complex your system is you might rely on
all of these testing steps and the
architecture it's it's a concern it's a
property of your architecture on how
easy it is to test it to verify that it
does what it's supposed to do right and
again this is a big topic that we'll
cover in future episodes specifically
there is one rather recent trend which
says that if you build your system so
it's easily testable then it's probably
well structured
so using testability as a means to drive
the quality of yet of your architecture
is something that has gained a lot of
importance recently and we'll cover that
in later episodes so now we covered
runtime and structural quality
attributes or operational and
developmental attributes and we briefly
want to mention some of the business
aspects although we
want to do that only briefly because I
mean this is a technical podcast we
don't want to talk too much about
business things but the point is that if
you consider things like time to market
or cost or the lifetime or the rollout
schedule of your of your system then
often those business-related
quality attributes or architectural
attributes are in conflict with some of
the technical attributes we discussed
before and in a minute we'll we'll
explain some of these conflicts a bit in
more detail the point is that those
business aspects are typically
represented and enforced and taken care
of by non-technical people ie managers
and that's also why some of them are in
conflict with with some of the technical
terms because different people different
interests different groups represent
them so you always have a conflict of
interest or at least a conflict of
viewpoints and and priorities yeah those
terms are time to market when are we
expected to deliver our solution to the
first customer its cost how many
resources how many developers can I
afford how many managers how what kind
of effort do I spend for testing it's
about a rollout schedule do I have to be
full up and running note failures you
know no box inside for when I start to
enter the market or can I afford to have
sign some box in there and do the final
system testing with the customers as
some big software vendors actually try
to do yeah Marcus I just want to add
that that's something we didn't talk
about before is quality in general so
there might be systems which do have
bugs but you will leave them in the
system because time to market is more
important so another quality attribute
is just the number of bugs in your
system and you might specifically want
to make compromises so you might want to
leave bugs in the system because fixing
the fixing them would be too costly or
would basically
kill your time to market yeah and
there's something that we suffer people
just learn to accept that basically no
system is free of tax you will always
haven't talked in there it will just
depends on how critical that Park will
be and how often or when it will occur
right back that nobody knows it just
probably doesn't matter all right so I I
had an idea about you mentioned that
only non-technical people are
responsible for those what I really
liked is when the technical lead or the
Software Architect actually got involved
in those business expects and was at
least involved in the discussions and
about that so that he he knew what under
which pressure he actually is and and
what are the concerns and and basically
the frame in which the development team
operates right I agree completely the
the point why I mentioned that before is
that in many projects that what you
described is not the case and therefore
a lot of problems result of course in a
good a well-managed project your
technical leaders will at least at least
the leaders will care about those
business aspects absolutely when
development is involved in this
discussion and it's just easier to deal
with the short time to market that we
always have and we just know what the
constraints are it's easier to deal with
them so one suggestion would be to make
those business aspects quite transparent
to the development team well not not
stress the development team but keep it
informed make it not worry about it but
make it know about it exactly I think
this distinction is really critical that
you have a kind of firewall between the
requirements and your customer and your
developers that doesn't mean that
developers should ignore these things or
not be told but somebody somewhere there
has to be some separation so that people
don't get as you said don't get stressed
all the time right
as we mentioned before those quality
attributes are of course at in an ideal
system you will have you know 100
of all of them well scalable no parks
very maintainable
but in practice that's often not
realistic so you have to strike a
compromise and basically say okay we
explicitly reduce this ility and
therefore increase another ility and so
as a consequence your system might
probably be for example less
maintainable but it might perform better
and we'll will come up with a couple of
examples and specific conflicts in a
minute the point is that you should make
those decisions explicit I mean
you shouldn't just build a system and
then at the end notice oh yeah it's not
maintainable but it's fast and that
might not be what you want but rather
you should discuss these things in the
beginning and say okay we our focus is
on for example performance and therefore
we'll explicitly make compromises with
regards to maintainability or
portability so yeah I actually like to
make my customers a priority a list of
all the ill at ease so that I know on
which to focus first on which to focus
next there must be just a straight order
and not just everything in parallel well
achieve scalability and performance and
maintainability at the same time this is
just not possible you have to balance
the forces and there will be a
preference you there's no way around it
right it's also one of these things
where you often have to educate your
customer and really make them think
about what they want and where their
priorities are right and another term
that comes actually bit from the pattern
community is balancing forces and so so
balancing forces in software
architecture is the is comparable to
balancing forces in a applying a pattern
to a design problem just at a larger
scale right so you have to make
trade-offs you have to make trade-offs
okay so let's maybe come to a couple of
typical compromises or trade-offs you
have to make when looking at the
relationships between a couple of
quality attributes and again each of us
will come up
an example in turn the first one is
performance versus scalability so for
example you might be able to find you
your system to a very specific
environment so that it comes with up
with a very very optimal performance but
scalability might be bad because if you
add additional load the system you know
queues might be full or some algorithms
might run out of their optimal
performance characteristics so the
system might not scale well although it
performs very well for a specific
situation the next conflict is
performance versus maintainability and
here for example to achieve high
maintainability a designer developer
might just decouple everything introduce
a lot of interfaces for example I saw
just recently and so-called
service-oriented architecture and that
wasn't service oriented architecture
down to two classes down to little small
responsibilities and the performance of
course then was not acceptable anymore
at all so this was just taking sua to an
extreme and where maintainability might
have been good because everything was
separated and with its own interface
ever actually its own remote interface
it was not performing anymore right
as usual if you overdose any medicine
it's probably going to be bad for you so
uh being the medicine here
another thing is performance versus
portability portability as we said
before is basically a kind of special
case of maintainability kind of so if
you want to be portable you usually have
to add all kinds of indirections
microkernels layers that that hide some
of the specifics of your underlying
platform environment and of course this
layering and this this separation of
concerns costs performance
there is one way how you can maybe solve
that for example if you have a C program
that should be portable you can have all
the various it's platform specifics
you know separated using if deaths and
these kinds of things then the system
might be portable as well as perform
well but then it's probably not very
maintainable because your code is
cluttered with all those if thefts and
stuff so so again you have to make
compromises somewhere the next is
availability versus performance and for
availability a typical thing to be which
is done to achieve high availability is
checkpointing that you in your regular
call and and control flow of the system
you store the state you persist state so
that when failure would occur it would
be easy to resume again so to minimize
the mean time to repair to be up and
running again in a consistent state and
so the problem here with performance
then is that those checkpoints that
persisting those checkpoints can be
quite expensive and so if you use check
pointing to extensive your performance
will be bad at the end another example
for this particular conflict
availability versus performance is also
for example if you have a system that
should be very very highly available
available then you probably have to have
redundant components like redundant
service or for example redundant
databases and depending on the level of
availability you would actually have to
have hot standby so that means that you
have the same information on both
components and that for example means
that whenever you do something in the
database you actually have to do it in
two databases using for example X the X
a transaction coordination protocol for
two-phase commit and that of course
introduces an overhead and your
performance will be reduced to
illustrate one of the conflicts between
the technical and business aspect if you
want to have a system that is more
available then you have to have you have
to make sure that there are fewer bugs
in it you
to probably have to have redundant
components as we mentioned before and
that of course drives cost so the more
available and the more reliable
a system should be the more expensive
it's going to be and that's nicely
illustrated if you take a look at
systems like I don't know never saw the
software of one of these but for example
the Space Shuttle or nuclear power
plants or life devices that that you
know pre keep you breathing during a
medical operation medical treatment of
course those systems have to be very
very reliable and very very available
and developing those systems is
extremely extremely expensive the next
conflict is about usability and versus
security and here a simple example is
when you increase the security of your
system you might require the user to
fill in all kind of passwords and tokens
and and generated IDs and this then
really conflicts with the usability when
a user like every day has to do that
procedure to access its data or to read
its email and hear features like single
sign-on or similar mechanisms help and
basically balance kind of those two
forces you get high security you but you
have to trust that the one signed-in
user actually stays to be that user and
has sufficient rights the classic
example of this usability versus
security is Microsoft Windows right they
edit the firewall only I think in XP
service pack 2 because although actually
they turned it on by default because
earlier Microsoft kind of decided that
they didn't want to bother their users
with all those you know prompts that
says hey there is some connection coming
in do you really want to accept the
connection and stuff so this was a
classical conflict between usability and
security so before we finish I guess we
should mention that there is also
sometimes the relationship between those
quality attributes where you don't have
a conscious
but rather where things support each
other for example maintainability can
help availability because if your system
fails if you have a maintainable system
it's faster to fix the problem so your
mean time or your actually your time to
re install a rerun or e to fix the
system is going down so your
maintainability goes up so it's not
always just conflicts so at this point
we want to stop for today this concludes
the episode number 2 on software
architecture and the next episode on
software architecture episode 3 we'll be
talking about how you can actually
achieve some of those quality attributes
and also show how to resolve some of the
conflicts that we mentioned in this
episode so thanks for listening see you
next time bye
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as lips and comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]